<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>jimmyff - lang-python</title>
    <subtitle>Fun loving creative (he&#x2F;him) 🏳️‍🌈</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.jimmyff.co.uk/tags/lang-python/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.jimmyff.co.uk"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2012-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jimmyff.co.uk/tags/lang-python/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>SublimeRsyncer - Rsync Plugin for SublimeText 2</title>
        <published>2012-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2012-05-30T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.jimmyff.co.uk/blog/sublimersyncer-rsync-plugin-sublimetext2/"/>
        <id>https://www.jimmyff.co.uk/blog/sublimersyncer-rsync-plugin-sublimetext2/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://www.jimmyff.co.uk/blog/sublimersyncer-rsync-plugin-sublimetext2/">&lt;p&gt;Discovering SublimeText 2 was love at first sight. It&#x27;s the fastest &amp;amp; most extensible IDE I&#x27;ve come across. Most of my projects reside on local virtual machines, I do this for development &amp;amp; production environment consistency, development machine portability and I don&#x27;t want to clutter up OSX, my desktop OS. This setup always results in an IDE headache: how to develop on OSX and automagically sync my changes to my various Linux VMs. When using Eclipse (my previous IDE of choice), I&#x27;d use the RSE plugin, which would allow me to have remote projects via SSH. SublimeText2 doesn&#x27;t offer many features out of the box and it&#x27;s left to you to choose how to setup your IDE by adding plugins. The plugin API is pretty simple, all python based so I decided to create a simple tool which would rsync my projects to my Linux VMs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;View&#x2F;Download Project: &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;github.com&#x2F;jimmyff&#x2F;SublimeRsyncer&quot;&gt;SublimeRsyncer on GitHub&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve not too much experience with Python so if this is your area you&#x27;ll probably cringe at my sloppy syntax and dodgy use of threading so not to block the UI. If you do make changes please hit me up with a pull request so I can incorporate your updates! :-)&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
