<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
    <title>jimmyff - neurodiversity</title>
    <subtitle>Fun loving creative (he&#x2F;him) 🏳️‍🌈</subtitle>
    <link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="https://www.jimmyff.co.uk/tags/neurodiversity/atom.xml"/>
    <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.jimmyff.co.uk"/>
    <generator uri="https://www.getzola.org/">Zola</generator>
    <updated>2023-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>https://www.jimmyff.co.uk/tags/neurodiversity/atom.xml</id>
    <entry xml:lang="en">
        <title>Neurodiversity: Dyslexia and ADHD</title>
        <published>2023-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</published>
        <updated>2023-07-02T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
        
        <author>
          <name>
            
              Unknown
            
          </name>
        </author>
        
        <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="https://www.jimmyff.co.uk/blog/neurodiversity-dyslexia-and-adhd/"/>
        <id>https://www.jimmyff.co.uk/blog/neurodiversity-dyslexia-and-adhd/</id>
        
        <content type="html" xml:base="https://www.jimmyff.co.uk/blog/neurodiversity-dyslexia-and-adhd/">&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Neurodiversity&lt;&#x2F;strong&gt; (&lt;em&gt;noun&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;) Variety in human behavioural traits and brain function, viewed as normal variation within the population.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly let me just say that writing a blog post about &#x27;me&#x27; feels a little self-indulgent. Despite this being my blog, I try not to include details about me or photos of me etc. I keep my socials locked down and try to keep my digital footprint minimal. I&#x27;m going to write this as I&#x27;d quite like to document how I feel and talking about this stuff is no bad thing.&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;hr &#x2F;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In case you don&#x27;t know me I better start by saying I&#x27;m in my late thirties and an all round content person. I was diagnosed with dyslexia when I was 14 and haven&#x27;t thought much of it since. I&#x27;ve just started the process of getting an ADHD diagnosis and this is how it came around:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For as long as I can remember I really get in to projects, like &lt;em&gt;really&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; into them, to the point I really struggle to sleep until I&#x27;ve finished them. I obsess over details and possible permutations and like a broken record I can&#x27;t change the track. I&#x27;ve previously questioned if I had OCD because it does feel like obsessions but that doesn&#x27;t fit as I don&#x27;t have any &#x27;compulsions&#x27;. I can&#x27;t choose what triggers these but it&#x27;s always something I find interesting -usually a creative endeavor. Thankfully these are usually work or hobby related which results in me being really productive. The downside of that is during these periods I sometimes go for weeks without proper sleep and I neglect other parts of life. I also generally feel frantic, it feels like my mind is always racing and moments of clam or silence are few and far between. I&#x27;ve previously questioned if this was normal but dismissed it as just being passionate about my projects.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Last week during a work related online conference the speaker talked about her ADHD &quot;fixations&quot; -what she described sounded very familiar to me. After the call I did a little research in to ADHD and the symptoms sounded as if someone who knew me really well was describing me. So many things I had put down to personality quirks were listed here (things like being a total over-thinker, frequently zoning out when people talk to me, forgetfulness, missing details &amp;amp; selective hearing, struggling with organising myself and neglecting general admin, can be socially clumsy -especially after a drink, real difficulty motivating myself to do something I don&#x27;t want to do, easily distractable when not working on something interesting, distracted by background sounds, even light-sensitivity!). Those &#x27;obsessions&#x27; I get are apparently known as &#x27;fixations&#x27; and the period of single-minded productivity is known as &#x27;hyper-focus&#x27;. The physically squirmy and fidgety symptom doesn&#x27;t fit me, but I do feel like that on a mental level -I struggle to sit though a film or watch TV for longer than an hour as it feels too passive. I&#x27;m still processing how I feel about it all, it&#x27;s great to have identified it as I can now learn more about it. However so much of what I thought was unique about me are symptoms of this thing that&#x27;s described as a &#x27;disorder&#x27; and &#x27;disability&#x27;!&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;adhd-clinical-diagnosis-connection-to-dyslexia&quot;&gt;ADHD clinical diagnosis &amp;amp; connection to dyslexia&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I tried a few of the ADHD online screening tools and I scored high-very high in each one. I&#x27;ve spoken to my local GP and she was very kind and has confirmed she will refer me for clinical diagnosis. There&#x27;s a 2+ years wait if I go with the NHS, or around an 18 months if I go use the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;adhduk.co.uk&#x2F;right-to-choose&#x2F;&quot;&gt;NHS Right to Choose&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; scheme which means they&#x27;ll cover the costs for a third party diagnoses via one of their selected partners.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GP was particularly interested in my Dyslexia asking a number of questions about it. She told me that there is a connection between Dsylexia and creativity. She also introduced me to the &lt;a href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;www.madebydyslexia.org&#x2F;&quot;&gt;#madebydyslexia&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; campaign that lists lots of innovators and creative thinkers such as Albert Einstein, Steve Jobbs and Richard Branson. I hadn&#x27;t spared my dyslexia any thought for my entire life, I just considered it as the annoying thing that meant I can&#x27;t spell and write like a child ...not as a character defining part of me! It turns out 30% of people with Dyslexia also have ADHD so there certainly seems to be correlation.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;so-what-now&quot;&gt;So what now?&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#x27;ve filled out the Right to Choose documentation and given it to the GP and I now need to wait for an unknown amount of time (suggestions are it could be anything from weeks to years). I&#x27;m not in a rush, I&#x27;ve got by fine for this long but learning more about it will certainly be welcome.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
</content>
        
    </entry>
</feed>
